Alexander Giovannelli

Phone: +1-740-258-9709 Email: agiovannelli@vt.edu Site: https://agiovannelli.github.io/

Summary

My research interest lies in the intersections of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Augmented/Virtual Reality (AR/VR), and 3D User Interfaces (3DUI) for collaboration. I am exploring how to improve asynchronous collaborative processes using immersive technologies. Specifically, I am prototyping and evaluating systems that capture presenter actions, providing supplemental visuals and interactive mechanisms for observer playback.

EDUCATION

Virginia Tech
Ph.D. in Computer Science advised by Doug A. Bowman, GPA: 4.00/4.00
Blacksburg, VA, USA
Aug. 2021–Present

University of Cincinnati

B.S. in Computer Engineering with German Studies minor, GPA: 3.30/4.00

Cincinnati, OH, USA

Aug. 2013–May 2018

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant

Virginia Tech

Blacksburg, VA, USA

Spring 2023 & Fall 2023

Investigated methods for asynchronous and synchronous collaboration in immersive experiences

- Performed contextual inquiry and analysis to determine research goals
- Created prototype virtual reality applications using C# and Unity technologies

Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory

Livermore, CA, USA

Computing Research Intern

Summer 2023

- Developed guided tour prototypes for inspection processes in virtual reality using C# and Unity technologies
- Facilitated meetings between multi-disciplinary project stakeholders
- Prepared user study procedure for evaluation of prototype capabilities

Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA, USA

Graduate Research Assistant

Summer 2022

- Conducted research regarding communication via avatars in augmented and virtual reality
- Generated prototype applications and experimental studies using C# and Unity technologies
- Designed and administered user studies in accordance with Institutional Review Board regulations

Work Experience

JPMorgan Chase & Co.

Columbus, OH, USA

Jul. 2018–Jul. 2021

Associate Software Engineer I

- Developed front-end features for Chase.com using JavaScript, HTML, and CSS technologies
- Designed and implemented minimum viable product user interfaces via Figma design tool
- Authored technical documentation for product owners and developers
- Appointed subject matter expert in behavioral-driven development and CI/CD initiatives
- Automated logging of proprietary systems using the Python programming language

Siemens Healthineers

Software Engineer Intern

Forchheim, BY, DE Jan. 2017–Aug. 2017

- Developed back-end software for use in advanced therapy devices using the C# programming language
- Created system architecture diagrams to record project design changes and behaviors
- Represented project team in international software integration meetings using German and English languages

Granville Exempted Village Schools

Granville, OH, USA

Systems Administrator Intern

May 2016-Jul. 2016

- Provisioned Windows and Linux server and workstation systems to support school network infrastructure
- Administered changes to proprietary devices regarding operating system applications, packages and images
- Managed summer technician team operations

Matrix Technologies, Inc.

Maumee, OH, USA

Aug. 2015–Dec. 2015

Computer Programmer and Systems Analyst Intern

- Created full-stack internal software tools for engineers and project managers using C#, XML and SQL
- Updated existing project management software according to submitted user feedback
- Authored software usage documents to elaborate on internal tool usage

Matrix Technologies, Inc.

Maumee, OH, USA

Aug. 2014–Dec. 2014

Computer Programmer and Systems Analyst Intern

- Enhanced existing proprietary software using the C# programming language
- Researched emerging technologies and presented potential process improvements for development team
- Coordinated project design changes with stakeholders

PUBLICATIONS

Peer Reviewed Journal Papers

J1. A. Giovannelli, J. Thomas, L. Lane, F. Rodrigues and D. A. Bowman, "Gestures vs. Emojis: Comparing Non-Verbal Reaction Visualizations for Immersive Collaboration," in *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics*, vol. 29, no. 11, pp. 4772-4781, Nov. 2023, doi: 10.1109/TVCG.2023.3320254.

Peer Reviewed Conference Papers

- C1. F. Rodrigues, A. Giovannelli, L. Pavanatto, H. Miao, J. C. d. Oliveira and D. A. Bowman, "AMP-IT and WISDOM: Improving 3D Manipulation for High-Precision Tasks in Virtual Reality," in 2023 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), Sydney, Australia, 2023, pp. 303-311, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR59233.2023.00045.
- C2. **A. Giovannelli**, L. Lisle, and D. A. Bowman, "Exploring the impact of visual information on intermittent typing in virtual reality", in 2022 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), 2022, pp. 8–17, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR55827.2022.00014.

Peer Reviewed Workshops, Posters, Abstracts, & Contests

- W1. I. A. Tahmid, F. Rodrigues, A. Giovannelli, L. Lisle, J. Thomas and D. A. Bowman, "CoLT: Enhancing Collaborative Literature Review Tasks with Synchronous and Asynchronous Awareness Across the Reality-Virtuality Continuum," in 2023 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality Adjunct (ISMAR-Adjunct), Sydney, Australia, 2023, pp. 831-836, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR-Adjunct60411.2023.00183.
- W2. A. Giovannelli, F. Rodrigues, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, L. Lane, C. Connor, K. Davidson, G. N. Ramirez, B. David-John, and D. A. Bowman, "Clue hog: An immersive competitive lock-unlock experience using hook on go-go technique for authentication in the metaverse", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 945-946, doi: 10.1109/VRW58643.2023.00315.

- W3. J. Thomas, S. W. Lee, **A. Giovannelli**, L. Lane, and D. Bowman, "A communication-focused framework for understanding immersive collaboration experiences", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 301–304, doi: 10.1109/VRW58643.2023.00070.
- W4. L. Lisle, F. Lu, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, A. Giovannelli, C. Llo, L. Pavanatto, L. Zhang, L. Schlueter, and D. A. Bowman, "Clean the ocean: An immersive vr experience proposing new modifications to go-go and wim techniques", in 2022 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2022, pp. 920–921, doi: 10.1109/VRW55335.2022.00311.
- W5. E. Mohammadrezaei, A. Giovannelli, L. Lane, and D. Gračanin, "A digital twin based approach to smart lighting design", in 2022 Winter Simulation Conference (WSC), 2022.

SKILLS

Programming Languages: C#, JavaScript, Java, Python, HTML, CSS

Productivity Tools: Unity, Git, JMP, SPSS, LaTeX, Tableau

Projects

• Gesture-based 3DUI for Arithmetic Operations Dec. 2023—Present

Design and prototyping of a virtual environment for embodied learning of arithmetic operations

• Guided Tours for Multiscale Collaborative Virtual Environments

— Jul. 2023—Present

— Design and prototyping of a virtual environment for collaboration in multiscale inspection processes

• Surface Generation for MR Remote Collaboration Jun. 2022–Sept. 2023

Prototyping and testing of multi-user environment for shared surface creation and collaboration

AWARDS

• I/ITSEC Leonard P. Gollobin Scholarship	2023
• Davenport Leadership Fellowship	2023 – 2024
• Best Conference Paper Honorable Mention IEEE ISMAR 2022 [C2]	2022
• Best 3DUI Contest Entry [W4]	2022
• International Co-op Program Scholarship	2016 – 2017
• Matrix Technologies, Inc. Co-op Scholarship	2014-2016

Professional Service

2 1001 2001011112 02101102		
• Committee Member		2024-Present
Inaugural member of the Virtual Experience Rese	earch Accelerator (VERA) Ethics and Privacy Comm	ittee
• Communications Chair		2023–Present
Develop and moderate discussion platforms for the	he IEEE VR 2024 conference	
• Student Volunteer		2023
Assist in event operations at IEEE International	Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality 2023	
• Student Volunteer		2023
Assist in event operations at IEEE VR 2023 sate	ellite event in Blacksburg, Virginia	
• Student Volunteer		2022
Assist in event operations at IEEE International	Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality 2022	
• Member of Computer Science Graduate Student	Council	2021–Present
Represent the interests of the CS graduate studen	nt body and assist in event planning	

• Member of the Center for Human-Computer Interaction

Active participant in the Center seminars regarding the study of human-computer interaction

2021-Present

Teaching

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Comparative Languages (CS-3304) Fall 2022

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Software Design & Data Structures (CS-2114) Fall 2021 & Spring 2022